<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title type="text">Diary - Morg Systems</title><id>https://morg.systems/Diary</id><updated>2024-07-03T19:39</updated><link href="https://morg.systems/Diary"/><icon>https://morg.systemsstatic/favicon.ico</icon><entry><id>https://morg.systems/I-don&#39;t-get-competitive-language-learning</id><title type="text">I don’t get competitive language learning</title><updated>2024-07-03T19:39</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The more I interact with the language learning community, the more I am convinced we are living through an epidemic of unhealthy competitiveness when it comes to learning languages. Maybe I’ve always been the odd one out when it comes to this stuff, although I know I am not the only one, but I have the feeling that the way most people approach language learning is just… incredibly twisted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the first moment I decided to learn Japanese, I never questioned the why or what of it. I just knew what I wanted to do, and I did it. At the time, I just thought about how I learned English, how most of my English learning outside of school has been me just playing videogames and reading a lot of books, and I just applied the same process to Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The very first day I completed kana, I just sat there and grabbed a manga and started reading. I didn’t question it. I didn’t worry about stats, numbers, difficulty metrics, vocabulary knowledge, anki cards, none of that stuff. To me it always felt obvious: I want to read manga, so I will read manga. I can just look up the stuff I don’t understand, so where is the problem?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Obviously, after months and years spent into the hobby, I now recognize I was very naive at the time. I should have put more thought into the proper study of grammar and structure, vocabulary learning, and followed a more methodical approach. But still, I am aware that being driven by just the sheer interest in Japanese media got me where I am now, and I wouldn’t have taken it any other way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And then, eventually, I started interacting with the larger Japanese learning community online. At the time I was already three years into Japanese learning. That’s when I realized most people don’t seem to be taking language learning the same way as I was. So many people treat it like an activity on its own, to improve on a skillset, to “level up”, to acquire knowledge, and to pad their own stats. I’ve been asked “How many words do you know?” as if that was a normal question to ask. How would I know? I never cared to count how many words I know in English, or in my native language, why would I do that for Japanese? How can you even tell if you know a word or not? I’ve been asked how fast I can read. How many characters per minute. How many books I’ve read, how many hours I have spent studying Japanese. “You guys measure all this stuff?” I thought.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This has always been completely alien to me because I’ve never really been in a real “language studying” moment, but rather I’ve always been in a “I need to understand this sentence because I want to read this book” mindset. I don’t care about the grammar. I don’t care about the words. I only care about the meaning and the enjoyment I can get out of it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, it would be incredibly hypocritical of me to not address the fact that I &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; do keep a spreadsheet tracking immersion time, I keep stats on books and manga read, games played, and I write about several resources for grammar study, research papers, and all kinds of linguistic stuff. But I am aware none of this is directly related to me learning Japanese. It’s all orthogonal and I consider it a new hobby I picked up along the way while I was interacting with the Japanese learning community (rather than Japanese itself). The distinction might feel hypocritical and it’s a bit nuanced, but in my mind the two things are clearly distinct. Let me put it this way: I am aware how much me rambling on this site and on discord is a pure waste of time with regards to my Japanese learning journey.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And yet, I see way too many people fall into the same trap without realizing it. Too many people focus on studying how to learn rather than just… learn. Be it an issue with motivation or discipline, there is an actual epidemic of language learners who are only learning because they like the idea of being a language learner, rather than having a goal in mind through which the language itself becomes just a means to an end.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What’s even worse, I have noticed over time that there’s this weird notion that language learning itself is structured in a straight line, going from point A to point B. There are two major contributors to this misconception:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Many people get stuck thinking about JLPT levels (or CEFR levels for other languages) and feel the need to measure their stats against such certifications&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Many people feel the need to compare other learner’s levels of skill, and square each other up as some kind of show of prowess. “I know more Japanese than you do”&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The unfortunate truth, however, is that languages cannot be measured so simply. Someone might be a genius at reading but completely unable to speak. Someone might be incredibly charismatic and awesome at giving public presentations, but completely unable to read. I could have a very thick accent but an insane ability at putting together words, while you might have perfect native-level phonetics but your word choice is completely lacking and broken. We all have our strengths and weaknesses, and there is no way to objectively measure each other up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And yet people do it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This often creates feelings of negative emotions which in turn also end up affecting how well we can acquire language. Even people who seem to thrive in competitive mindsets (“I need to become better than him at phonetics so I will do more pitch accent awareness drills!!”), in my opinion, end up missing the forest for the trees. They think their eyes are on the prize, but they are not looking at what should be their prize. They aren’t building that sense of independence and detachment from language learning platforms and communities that they need to achieve in order to thrive in the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; language.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t really have any closure to this post, it’s been mostly just a personal rant that I wanted to get off my chest, but if there’s one thing I wish more people understood is to stop worrying so much. Just go out there and enjoy &lt;em&gt;doing stuff&lt;/em&gt;. Don’t study the language. Ignore the language. The language is not what you should worry about. Find something you like doing, and do that. In the language you’re learning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only then will you achieve enlightenment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://morg.systems/I-don&#39;t-get-competitive-language-learning"/></entry><entry><id>https://morg.systems/Language-learning-is-a-great-excuse-for-escapism</id><title type="text">Language learning is a great excuse for escapism</title><updated>2023-06-13T08:02</updated><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever since I was little I’ve always loved reading books. I was a very early reader: I remember learning to read when I was 3 by trying to hammer keys on my old DOS computer to get into Windows so I could play with Paint (people my generation who had a PC back then will understand). I slowly discovered what each letter looked like on the keys and eventually figured out how to read like that. Then, in elementary school, I got hooked on fantasy books (series like Shannara) and my life has never been the same since. I remember my teachers being annoyed at me for choosing to read books rather than play with other kids during recess, but I really needed to know how the story ended and I was fully immersed in that world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As I grew up, in my teenage years, I began to read books in English. This was mostly for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The translation of some books I read in Italian was very wrong. While I appreciate and admire the work of translators, those books I read were really badly translated, and discovering the original work really opened a new world to me.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The English version was, ironically, cheaper to buy in the store. It was an age before digital reading and ebooks, and as a teenager with not a lot of money to spend, saving every penny helped. The English version was much cheaper than the Italian one, because not many people in Italy bought books in English at the time anyway.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the side, while I was enjoying books, I also got into videogames and gaming, mostly JRPGs. I’ve always been fascinated the most by the narrative and storytelling rather than the gameplay. If a game has a good and compelling story to me, it can be a great game even if the gameplay is mediocre. It’s another great chance to immerse and discover a new world, like an interactive book.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After graduating highschool, for a reason I don’t really know, I somewhat grew away from books and reading as a hobby. I spent most of my time doing game development and programming, studied computer science in university, and got started in my current career. I also nurtured my other hobby which is guitar and music production.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A lot of my time in my 20s was spent traveling (for work), living abroad, practicing music, and also playing &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of CSGO. I don’t think there was any real reason why I grew away from reading but it just happened and I always assumed it was a thing adults did. I’ve always heard people say “I don’t have time for reading as an adult” and similar excuses and I kinda internalized them myself too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, my late 20s/early 30s hit, and I got into Japanese learning. Japanese learning changed my world once again (for the better or worse I can’t tell yet, but probably for the better). I was already familiar with the idea that if you want to learn a language well you need to live it, and that the best way to live it is by reading and immersing in that language’s media, so that did not come as a surprise to me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What surprised me, however, was how &lt;strong&gt;good&lt;/strong&gt; it felt to get back into reading as a hobby without feeling like I was “wasting time”. I could excuse my reading by telling myself “It’s for language learning” and just spend hours upon hours immersed in manga, books, games, etc guilt free. It gave me back a feeling that I had forgotten: the feeling of escaping the current world and joining adventures and stories from faraway lands full of unknowns. It brought me back to my teenage years of blissful fantasy reading and story-focused gaming.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Language learning is an amazing way to not only learn about a new culture and interface yourself with a foreign world, but also to give yourself a chance to catch a breath in this modern frantic world and tell yourself that it’s okay to just open a book and read. You owe it to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’ve never enjoyed reading, I think you’re missing out and you should give it another chance. If you used to enjoy reading and ended up growing away from it, consider coming back. It is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://morg.systems/Language-learning-is-a-great-excuse-for-escapism"/></entry></feed>